So the appendix is on the fundamental
theorem of algebra. So as a dessert you
will take home the knowledge of why this
famous theorem is true. Not just that it
is true.
and I'll put it between quotation marks
the fundamental so-called fundamental
theorem of algebra. Okay.
As you know the theorem says the
following. Let's say that f of zed I
shall write it down explicitly cd and z
d plus c d minus one z dus one and so on
to c1 z + c 0
is a complex polinomial.
of degree
D which is greater than or equal to one.
Often people forget to state this
hypothesis. When I stated for example a
minute ago I forgot to mention it
because a degree zero polinomial is a
constant. For example, take the constant
two. Well, this constant polinomial 2
doesn't have a root anywhere. You see?
So the fundamental theorem algebra works
only when the degree is greater than or
equal to one. Okay. And the theorem is
that
there exists some complex number
such that f of zed is zero. You know
proof
I shall draw a large picture here. Let's
say that this is the origin
and take the a point zed
and let's go around the circle
once.
Okay.
So assume for contradiction.
I'll show you the picture in a moment.
that um for all zed
f of zed is non zero.
Okay.
Now
this um proof depends on the following
fact
which I shall first discuss
intuitively. Thank you very much. um
look at this point
and consider a loop which does this.
It's not quite circular. How many times
did I go around this loop? Did I go
around this point once? Let's say that
we count it as plus one. If I went
around in the anticlockwise
counterclockwise direction, okay, how
many times did I go around?
Minus one time. Okay. How many times did
I go around?
Plus two. Now a tricky one.
How many times did I go around?
Minus one. That's good. Okay,
here is a really tricky one.
How many times did I go around? I passed
this through this.
Well, it's not clear, right? Because
let's compare this with two other
scenarios. Suppose that I go
like this. How many times did I go
around? I went around like this. Minus
one.
But let's do like this.
Do you see it's + one in this case? So
that's + one. That's minus one. How do
we count to this? There's a
discontinuity as you can see as I move
this picture a little bit.
Are you with me? We cannot in fact
define how many times we went around in
this case.
If you pass through the point, you lose
track of the count. Anyway, you cannot
define sensibly a rotation number how
many times you went around in a
continuous way. Is that okay? Good. So
please bear that in mind and let's come
back to the proof of the fundamental
theorem of algebra. So let's assume that
there is no zero there's no root. Now as
the
point Z
which I write in the polar form as R * E
to I theta
revolves
around the origin
zero once which is what we do and we are
saying that this radius is R. Okay,
let us look at what does Z to D. Zed to
D is R2D * E2 I d theta. You can think
of the case when D equ= 2. For example,
when zed goes around the origin once,
what does Z² do?
H
this is the radius RD. What does Z
square do? It starts from here and then
don't you know look at e to i theta it
becomes e to i d theta you are going
around with d times the angular speed
at the distance rd so if these two what
happens when zed goes around once what
does d square do
it goes around twice that's correct so
you get the picture like this goes
around And while zed is going around
once the its image you should imagine a
movie goes around goes around in fact
it's going around along the same
trajectory but in order to show you that
it's going around twice I'm drawing them
slightly differently but in reality it's
exactly the same curve that it's tracing
twice and then it comes back and then
returns to the initial point. Okay, it
goes around twice. So this is what for
example if zed is here maybe zed squared
will be um
somewhere here
this is not a very good picture. So zed
squ
okay it goes around.
So in general d times
around the origin and
f of zed
well it's a complex number right so I
don't know what it does but anyway it's
going to go around the origin a number
of times
okay I don't know where what f of zed
does while zed goes around once maybe
goes somewhere and you know goes on a
hike up the Misenberg mountain and then
comes back and and then goes back to bed
and then you know comes to class and who
knows I mean it goes but when zed
completes a turn zed of f of zed returns
to where it started okay so it draws a
curve which closes up a loop so it goes
around the origin a certain number of
times so revolves
a certain number
which we shall call
n r because it depends on r you see if r
is different maybe f is going to be
different but it doesn't depend on theta
because I'm going around around once
anyway so a certain number
n sub r times
around the origin
okay
however this is where we are going to
get the contrad prediction. So please be
careful.
We were assuming that f of zed is all
always non zero. In particular, when f
of zed goes on a hike and comes back and
comes back to class and goes to bed and
and and so on and goes back to where it
started to complete the loop, this
curve, this loop never goes through the
origin.
Okay? Therefore, we can count this
number
n.
If it went through the origin as we saw
this number cannot be counted. It would
be impossible to define this number
continuously. Is that okay? So because
of this hypothesis that it it's every
non vanishing
this
nr is well defined. That's the
expression in mathematics. So there is
no problem defining this number. Whereas
if f vanished became zero somewhere you
cannot define this number. So the proof
stops there. You cannot say it involves
a certain number of times because we
cannot define this number. But as it is
because we assuming that f of zed is
every un zero, we can continue the
proof. Logic does not stop. Okay. So is
well defined because precisely
by assumption
f of z never
passes through
through zero. Correct?
Okay.
Well, now we are ready to hit the main
part.
Let's look at the case
R equals Z and then start increasing R
more and more. We are deforming the
picture and we'll see that there's a
contradiction
when R equals Z. Well, zed reduces to a
single point, right? So
f of z
which is f of zero. So I don't know
where f of z is maybe somewhere here or
somewhere here somewhere here. In fact f
of0 is going to be c of z whatever it
is. Okay. So f of0 um reduces to a
single point. So let me write it a bit
more um in a more civilized way. So f of
zero
reduces
to a single point
which is f of zero. Yeah f of z actually
reduce a single point f of zero. So
naturally
what's the n of zero? How many times did
f go around the origin?
Well if I stay there how many times do I
go around the origin? Zero times. So
this is zero.
Okay. On the other hand,
if r is very large,
this is my notation for very large.
Okay. Well, what is f of zed then? When
zed is very large
in that expression we wrote
this is the highest order term and all
the other lower order terms. So if zed
is huge this term is going to dominate
and the others will be insignificant.
One way to see if you are a little
nervous is to write this as c d z d and
you factor it and then you get 1 + c of
d - 1 / z plus c of d minus 2 / z^² and
so on right and if zed is huge all of
these will be very small. So this will
be approximately equal to one. So indeed
this dominates is that okay? So in this
case f of zed is approximately cd * z d
you don't have to worry about cd. So
this one you see goes around origin
how many times it's essentially z d how
many times do I go around origin d
times. So this is D H and remember that
this D is greater than equal to one.
But look the number of times I go around
the origin is a continuous function of
the loop that we are taking. Right? If I
modify the loop a little bit, it's still
the same number of times we go through
the origin.
So
n subr and depends continuously
on r
and it cannot jump
from zero to d because d is greater than
equal to
depends sorry so it's a sorry is an
integer
depending continuously on r
the principle we are using here is a
very famous principle you know all about
continuous function you can kind of
imagine the graph of continuous function
please imagine that you have a
continuous function but whose values are
all integers.
What can you say about this function?
Constant. Can you see that? A continuous
function which takes values only among
integers.
It must be constant because if it's not
constant, that means that here it takes
some value. Here it takes some value.
But this value is an integer. This value
is an integer. And it cannot do this
because it has to take integer values
everywhere. So the only option is for it
to jump from here to here which is not
continuous. Okay. So constant functions
that are continuous uh sorry integer
valid functions that are continuous must
be constant and so you cannot jump from
zero to d.
Yeah as
r varies.
But we seem to have observed that it
jumped from zero to d when r is zero. n
of z is zero when uh so this is excuse
me
um r is very large n of r is d
what happened something went wrong it's
a contradiction
and the contradiction came from
that offending assumption that there is
sorry that offending assumption that
there is no root to the point
because we made that assumption this n
could be well defined logic took us
through this step
and we are forced to conclude by the
deformation argument that this cannot
happen. Okay, a contradiction
establishing the fundamental theorem of
algebra.
Okay.
Well, I hope you can take it home and
enjoy.
Good.
Let us then finish.
As I said, tomorrow I'll give you a
quick review of everything that we did
and then show you something
entertaining. But
just to finish, you know, when we
started the course 3 weeks ago
on the 6th of January, was it? It feels
like a long time ago,
but it's so short.
Do you remember the first problem that
we discussed? We discussed so the square
or the disc and can you connect those
two points and this point and this point
and this point this point with
continuous curves so that they don't
over intersect and so on. You remember
this and we saw it was a cute problem
that by deforming the picture you could
solve and by deforming back you got the
solution.
Let me give you another puzzle.
Okay.
And I want you to work on it for maybe
five or 10 minutes and then we'll take a
break. Well, then I'll give you a
solution and we take a break. All right.
Let's consider the following picture.
Um I'm going to draw the picture in a
certain order so as to make a beautiful
picture.
Let's have a rectangle, yellow rectangle
with sides are A and B.
Okay. So inside
a rectangle
of size
AB,
inscribe an ellipse.
H, you know what that means? I draw an
ellipse which touches the rectangle on
all sides. There exist a unique ellipse
like this. You can always do this and
there's only one inscribe
an ellipse
and if you work quite hard you can um
write down the equations of this ellip
equation of this ellipse and so on.
Okay. And then inside apes
inscribe
another rectangle.
So here the first rectangle was drawn in
yellow and the second rectangle will be
drawn in red or pink.
which is similar to the original
rectangle.
I hope the meaning is clear. So here I
could draw lots and lots of rectangles
incribe. For example, I could draw a
rectangle like this. I could draw a
rectangle like this. But please draw a
smaller rectangle which is similar to
the outside rectangle. In other words,
the ratio of this side to this side is
always a to b. Is that okay?
Question.
What is the ratio of areas of the big
rectangle to the small rectangle? So,
what's the area of the um big one
compared with the
area of the small one?
What is this?
Please work together and try to solve.
Go on. Go on. I'll give you the solution
in about 7 minutes. Have you started
doing some calculations?
square first.
Yeah, you try to do it the square first.
Okay. And have you progress?
Is everyone suffering?
Good.
Okay. Everyone is suffering
because my purpose is not to make
everyone suffer.
You might think, you might have the
impression that that it is, but in fact
it isn't. Um because my purpose is not
to make everyone suffer, but to teach
something interesting to everyone. Let's
stop.
We know in you know suppose that our
life depended on it. Suppose that if we
cannot find this ratio of areas
correctly and as releases a lion which
will eat me up.
Then I will certainly calculate right. I
can maybe say that okay those are the
axis. I can calculate the equation of
this ellipse and then I can find out
where those four corners are. Yes. And
then I can multiply and so forth. Yes.
But as it happens, Barry Green is a very
very good director and will not release
a lie on me.
So let's think one last time
topologically.
What happened to you?
Do I have any yellow left? What happened
to my yellow choke? It would be nice.
I must have I I know that the yellow
choke exists because I use it. Ah here
it is. Thank you very much. Um
first we shall say that well this
problem looks difficult so we are going
to deform the problem.
Okay,
this is the original problem
and we want the
area of yellow big thing over the
area of the small rectangle.
Okay,
this side is A. This side is B. But
let's squeeze this side
until this side also becomes B. Or
equivalently, let's stretch this side so
that this side also becomes A. Okay.
So this picture can be deformed to the
following picture.
where both sides are a in other words
it's a square and the circle with
another sort of square inscribed in the
middle in the course of this deformation
the ratio of areas does not change
is that okay because I'm just scaling
one direction by by some factor is that
okay so the area of this big square over
the area of this small square
is exactly the same as the previous
area. So this area if you the ratio of
areas is invariant under this
deformation.
Now what is the ratio of areas between
the large and small? Well, still it
looks difficult.
Yes,
still it looks difficult. So I'm going
to deform the problem again. Please
watch what I'm going to do. This is a
large box. I have a circle inscribed in
it. Excuse me.
Okay.
Circle like this. And I'm going to take
this middle red square and rotate it by
90°.
Huh?
and I have this
square.
Okay. And if you want you can think of
those lines cutting when I do this. Of
course, the area of the outer yet box
divided by the area of the middle now
90° rotated by small box. This ratio is
of course the same as the previous
ratio. Yes. But look what's the ratio.
Look at this.
That's a triangle and that's a box.
Do you see the ratio? It's equal to what
is it? Two.